[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software hello this is Charles
Anderson for software engineering radio
today we were talking to Charles Nutter
from Red Hat do you mind if I call you
Charlie yeah that's just fine great at
Red Hat Charlie works on jvm languages
focusing on JRuby he has also worked on
JRuby for engine yard and Sun
Microsystems he has been a java virtual
machine enthusiast
since Java 1.0 Charlie works to make
JRuby the best Ruby implementation for
high performance big data and heavy
loads and to use the lessons learned
from JRuby to help the JVM and other
languages that run on it meet their
potential today we will be talking about
the JVM as a language platform
welcome to software engineering radio
charlie thanks I'm glad to be here okay
so let's kind of sort of start out at
the very highest level what are the
components of the Java platform well I
always think about the the Java platform
as three pieces
there's the java language or whatever
language you happen to be writing on top
of the platform there are the libraries
that have been written for the the
platform which can include the jdk
libraries themselves java dot whatever
and all the other libraries that are out
there the tens of thousands of libraries
people have written and then probably
the most important part of that is the
the JVM the third piece which makes
everything run and the language in the
libraries may be the same across
different runtimes across different JVMs
but each of the JVM runs things a little
bit differently with different goals in
mind okay and so what are the
attractions of developing on top of the
JVM well like any any good managed
runtime the JVM provides garbage
collection automatic memory management
it provides a JIT that can turn JVM
bytecode into native code optimized
native code
obviously the the wealth of libraries
that are out there a big part of it
folks that use JRuby often will come to
us because there's a JVM library that
doesn't exist in the Ruby world so with
those three things we kind of have it
have a good selling point for for
building languages on top of the JVM now
in some cases like with Ruby the
original language is also not
multi-threaded or its multi-threaded but
not really parallel that's something
else we get out of the JVM it's been
multi-threaded truly parallel for years
and it's really battle-tested so
bringing Ruby to the JVM also gives it
real native threads do you often have a
guess as to how many languages there are
besides Java on the JVM these days
well we've we've tried to track this a
little bit over time there's no
canonical list of all these languages
but people periodically do put put
together lists there's there's a couple
that are on Wikipedia as well and it's
definitely in the neighborhood of
hundreds it was over 200 length like
registered or known language
implementations when we started really
hitting JRuby hard and working on it
hard in 2006 so there's more now if it
continues to grow over time it's
probably you know 250 300 languages that
are available all right and is there any
sort of taxonomy that at a very high
level one could apply to the languages
well so every language that gets written
for the JVM is going to be a managed
environment so there are implementations
of languages like C and C++ that can
sort of compile to the JVM but generally
it's going to be unmanaged or it's gonna
be managed languages with managed memory
or what memory management taken care of
for for you there's also the static and
dynamic typing languages statically
typed language is certainly easier to
get onto the JVM since it's it's kind of
a statically typed runtime but lots of
dynamic language implementations like
Ruby and groovy and whatnot and I think
closure kind of qualifies as a dynamic
dynamic language as well outside of that
a you know it's it's the same as Tecton
taxonomy z' for languages on other
platforms there's no like I said there's
not very many lists out there that show
all of the different languages but most
of the the interesting ones people have
heard of like Scala and closure
and JRuby right yeah those are later on
I kind of asked a little bit about those
I think of those as if you will kind of
professional languages and then there
are languages that are aimed at research
kind of projects and then I suppose also
sort of hobby languages I mean given
that there's hundreds of them on that
JVM many of which will never hear yeah
sure well there's there's toy languages
and experimental languages all over the
place on the JVM too so it's a lot of
experimentation it's really a nice
platform to target for a language
because of all the bonus benefits it
gives you and it's pretty easy to get a
language going so lots of experiments -
okay great when the JVM was created was
it intended to support multiple
languages well so if you actually go
back and look at the early revisions of
the J the JVM specification they did
have language in there saying perhaps in
the future we may extend the
specification to support more languages
or to have features that that newer
newer languages might need so they were
thinking about it from the beginning
none of those enhancements actually
happened until about 2007 2008 when we
started to get Java 7 work going on with
invokedynamic
making dynamic dispatch actually a fast
and optimized feature of the JVM so it
took a while for some of those extended
features to come along but I think they
knew this platform was going to be good
for languages even in the beginning it
has son and now Oracle be been very
supportive of languages other than Java
on their JVM or has it been sort of a
politely tolerating I think it was
probably politely tolerating or just
ignoring up until 2005 2006 or so at
that point folks like John Rose and Tim
Bray who were language advocates and
working at Sun Microsystems decided it
was time for us to start doing a little
bit more that's when the invokedynamic
work started that's when Tom Anna Bo the
other JRuby co-lead and I were hired by
sun to work on languages and work on
specifically JRuby so
since then the support has been really
tremendous JRuby is used as a regression
case for new versions of Java new JVM
features they're working on they use it
for performance testing they use it for
kind of punishing the JVM with some of
the more interesting tricks that we use
and they've been working independently
on language support within Oracle
they've done a JavaScript implementation
that is extremely fast they're working
on new language runtimes to make more
dynamic languages work fast on the JVM
so I'd say they've been very supportive
yeah and it's it's been a great 10 years
to work on this stuff oh that kind of
surprises me I would have thought if
anything it would have been kind of the
opposite that in the early quote hippy
unquote days under sun that it might
have been a little freer and then under
the corporate days of oracle would be a
little more locked down but good news
there yeah I think maybe the fact that
you know in the late to late 90s the
early 2000s Java was still considered a
cool language by a certain number of
developers out there and you know it
wasn't as reviled as it is these days
and they were fine using Java towards
the middle 2000s people started to
realize okay there's a lot of other cool
languages out there there's a lot of
features from new languages that were
not getting in Java and both Oracle and
Sun I think recognized at that point
that the platform can be more than just
Java oh yeah that makes perfect sense
yeah now that you mention it those those
time frames make perfect sense I guess
in the rear view mirror so as a case
study for developing a language on the
JVM let's look at JRuby I mean you were
just saying that in a way Oracle uses it
as a case study for testing and what
what not so what for our listeners who
might not be familiar
what exactly is JRuby so JRuby is
literally a ruby implementation on top
of the JVM we tried to keep it mostly
pure Java or you know pure JVM bytecode
but there are some features that have
native libraries that we call out to
specifically for integrating with the
platform but yeah we've tried to do as
much as possible to make it look and
feel and behave just like regular Ruby
all the way from the command line up
through the libraries that are available
it's just Ruby on the JVM all right can
you give us a brief history of its
development I mean you mentioned
beginning working on it and like the
2006 timeframe or so right so JRuby the
project has actually existed for a bit
longer than that
the first commit is in fall of 2001 well
initially I think they were mostly just
trying to get a good Ruby parser on the
JVM perhaps for tooling and other other
purposes like that but over the years
they did okay got a parser well maybe we
can actually build a runtime for this
and when I got involved in the project
in 2004 and 2005 it was roughly
compatible with Ruby 186 it was missing
many many features it didn't run most
standard Ruby code that was out there
and I thought there was a lot of
potential in this I thought we could
make this be one of the best Ruby
runtimes or the best Ruby runtime so
then 2005 I really started working on it
hard my friend and co-lead Tom Anna Bo
who was already working on the project
we started really pushing forward trying
to get rails to run trying to get things
to run fast and then in 2006 we were
hired on full-time by Sun Microsystems
to keep doing what we were already doing
and that's that's been ten years of
full-time work on JRuby since then and
then in case it is an obvious we can
just state the JRuby is open source
right right open source this the main
license is eclipse public license so
it's not a copyleft license it's one of
the more business-friendly licenses but
we also can we also release the source
under GPL - and LGPL - for folks that
need those licenses right so where did
the majority of JRuby users come from
are they coming from a Java world or are
they coming from Ruby world well it goes
where it goes around and around so when
ruby really started to get popular in
2005-2006 lots of rubyists were java
expats they had left the platform and
looking for something better they wanted
to do web development that wasn't
verbose as it wasn't Java so they went
to Rails so there's a lot of folks in
the Ruby community that that were ex
Java people I would say that most of our
users have come either from Ruby as
former Java users or they're just plain
rubyists that need a better runtime we
do have people that will come from Java
to Ruby but it's usually just more of a
decision that they want to use Ruby
whether than specifically JRuby and and
JRuby just fits into their JVM world
better so most of the time it's people
that know Ruby already and want
something a little bit more powerful
okay in the beginning of 2016 JRuby 9000
was released that's a pretty impressive
number what was that so we for about the
first three quarters of 2016 we were
working on the the current major version
of JRuby which we codenamed JRuby 9000
the name was intended as a joke
initially because we couldn't decide
whether to use what what version number
to use 1.8 would have conflicted with
ruby 1.8 and we weren't gonna be much
newer than that 2.0 would have clinique
flickered with ruby 2.0 and we didn't
want to confuse people so we went with
9000 and eventually it turned out that
this was going to be our ninth major
release so it kind of turned into JRuby
9.0 dot 0 dot 0 and what JRuby 9000
actually is it's in its many years
probably three or four years worth of
work on a completely new runtime for
JRuby before we would parse code in we'd
have an ast in memory the interpreter
would just walk that ast for a while and
then a very naive JIT that would turn
that ast into JVM bytecode for the JVM
to run the new version has it's in its
own intermediate representation like a
standard optimizing compiler we have
optimization passes control flow graph
data flow graph
lots more tools to analyze and optimize
Ruby code before we even give it to the
JVM and so then the JIT doesn't have to
do as much work the JVM can do a better
job of optimizing Ruby and it's really
starting to pay off now with the most
recent 9.1 release
all right that makes sense you're
getting a little ahead of me I
eventually want to get into some some of
those details and whatnot but how has
the JVM aided the development of the
JRuby implementation versus a native
runtime like the standard Ruby MRI
interpreter well if you look at the
development of the other Ruby runtimes
that have to be a basically be building
their own VM they spend a tremendous
amount of time trying to find ways to
optimize that code if it's a runtime
with a JIT they have to write their own
JIT in their own native code generation
maybe maybe based on LLVM maybe
something hand-rolled they have to write
and debug their own GCS and G CSR that's
it's a career-maker those are those are
some things that you work on your entire
life to get a really solid generational
concurrent garbage collector those
things we get for free we get a nice
chip that can do native code we get
excellent garbage collectors we get a
massive array of tools that have to be
written by hand written by it from
scratch for the other runtimes so all of
those things that bootstrap a managed
environment we get for free and that
really makes a huge difference we can
focus on the performance of the language
itself and on making better versions of
all the core libraries oh yeah great and
then I suppose also you you get things
like the Java performance tooling and
whatnot right yeah exactly pretty much
any tool that you can use with Java you
can use with Ruby so remote monitoring
performance monitoring heap dump heap
analysis all this stuff works right
alongside Ruby code yeah I seem to
recall one of the newer releases of Ruby
they were talking about some new garbage
collection mechanism being available and
just kind of thinking to myself if
memory serves that was sort of thing was
available in Java maybe ten years ago or
something right right yeah Ruby 2.2 they
added a sort of a pseudo generational
garbage collector it will transplant
objects that it it knows are safe that
the C world hasn't
seen that extensions haven't seen so
they can do a little bit of generational
juggling around but it's still way
behind what you have on the JVM I mean
there's there's whole teams of people
that work on JVM garbage collectors for
years right yeah big teams that have
been working for years and years I'm
writing you know writing their doctorate
on this new to garbage collector
technology so this is this is where
garbage collection lives really yeah
exactly
I've seen you speak on the difficulties
of duplicating the semantics of Ruby in
JRuby in what ways does the JVM make
development harder well the fact that
the JVM is kind of platform agnostic is
is a mixed blessing there are features
that people will expect to behave on a
platform specific basis the biggest ones
we've run into is a lot of the the
standard POSIX API s Lib C api's and
things that are missing on Java like
until recently no support for looking up
and managing siblings or all the
possible permissions that might be on a
UNIX file system getting Ruby to Ruby
Ruby has its own notion of what a string
is a string is an array of bytes and
then one of a couple dozen different
encodings that it provides well on Java
all strings are utf-16 character strings
so we had to implement our own string
implementation to support all that those
in codings even just down to the
language level there's features in Ruby
and and many other dynamic languages
like closures that don't have a good
analog on the JVM so in order for us to
have closures and and capture local
variables we need to allocate some
structure put that on the heap and then
that has to be managed and an extra
overhead for the JVM some of these
things are improving they are working on
making the JVM fit these other Ruby
features some of the pose extend ativ
integration Java itself actually is
going to have a byte array based string
internally that maybe will be exposed at
some point but yeah it's kind of it's
really at those edges io native library
support the things that really touched
the system have been wrapped up so
neatly on the JVM that
we can't get the features we need right
yeah the deposit stuff was pretty
obvious to me but I I was surprised when
I heard you speaking about the
difficulties of sprint of strings
because neither one of the platforms
treats or neither one of the languages
JRuby Ruby or Java treats a string as
7-bit us-ascii
so I had never considered that given
that they had more modern
representations that there would be
someone so many difficulties yeah the
string things kind of kind of odd
because they could have probably settled
on a single encoding like the JVM but
they also use string as a whole as a
container for binary data there is no
separate byte string so they had to at
least be able to support arbitrary
unencoded bytes alongside at least one
encoding of character data and then due
to various issues nobody could agree on
whether it should be utf-8 or something
else so they kind of went with a more
complicated implementation that supports
pretty much all encodings at the same
time okay is JRuby itself written in
Java or JRuby is it self hosting I think
you said it was written in Java right
yeah so the majority of JRuby is written
in Java obviously the the actual runtime
the interpreter for Ruby code the parser
and the compiler that's all Java code
the core classes like string and hash
and array are mostly written in Java but
more and more we've been adding as new
features come along for Ruby we often
will add them as a ruby implementation
to try and host a little bit more of Jay
Ruby's implementation in Ruby itself
okay and then perhaps if it turns out to
be a performance bottleneck redo it in
Java yeah exactly so we'll first simple
like a feature that comes to mind
spawning an external process so already
spawning an external process is pretty
heavy to do in the first place so having
that as a bit of Ruby code that does the
the actual process launch an argument
processing is not as big of a hit now if
it was a numeric operation
we probably want to have a native
version of that right yeah that makes
perfect sense do you find that Java's
original promise of write once run
anywhere work for either the JRuby
compiler or applications that people
write using JRuby that's it's actually
been great for us JRuby is today
probably the best way to run Ruby on
Windows because most of the core Ruby
developers run on UNIX most of the
libraries get tested on UNIX and they
will run into odd platform problems that
just don't work on Windows so Jay Ruby's
been great for that we also don't have
to worry about making binaries for every
platform we ship one Java compiled jar
file class files and it will work
anywhere that there's a JVM the JVM guys
have kind of taken the the hard work out
of porting across platforms and done
that for us yeah that's true that's
that's a yet another great benefit of
the JVM yes definitely what about if if
somebody's developing a JRuby app and
they've got some Ruby library that they
want to use and or its dependencies what
sort of portability issues do you run
into there I mean we already kind of
talked about like POSIX stuff possibly
or string stuff that JRuby is taken care
of right so if it's a piece if it's part
of Ruby that is proscribed behavior that
we're not matching we bend over
backwards to make it work we would
consider that a bug in almost every case
and try to make sure that JRuby matches
however C Ruby does it however sometimes
the libraries are written with only UNIX
in mind they're using Ruby features or
native features that aren't going to
work on Windows in the in that case the
code may run fine on JRuby but they're
going to be hitting stuff that doesn't
do the same as it would on a UNIX system
there are also libraries that have
native code in C Ruby we don't run that
native code we have our own extension
API that's also
for Java or other jvm languages rather
than C so those libraries sometimes you
can't even get them to run on Windows at
all with C Ruby but if we have a JRuby
equivalent we're already ahead of the
game it's just gonna be JVM bytecode and
our extensions will work while C Ruby's
won't again makes perfect sense I would
also think that sometimes thread safety
is an issue just because of the Ruby
library coming from an environment like
you said where threading is whatever you
want to call a second-class citizen or
an afterthought and so maybe the
libraries aren't thread safe and then
suddenly you put them into a
multi-threaded environment that would be
an issue yes so that happened a lot more
in the early days of JRuby people were
writing stuff that just for simplicity
and because it didn't didn't break on
MRI they would write stuff that uses a
lot of global State they'd have global
variables or they'd have constants which
are essentially just a value stuck into
a class somewhere and they would be
modifying that for multiple threads over
the past ten years we've managed to do a
lot of Education of the Ruby community
how to write good thread safe code what
not to do and the libraries have
improved tremendously there's a library
called concurrent Ruby available now
that basically has all the possible
concurrency patterns implemented there's
futures there's promises
there's thread pools there's thread safe
collections all of this stuff in one
library that pretty much everyone is
using now and that's given people better
tools to go along with our our
recommendations in our education these
days we don't run into thread safety
problems in Ruby libraries as often they
do come up once in a while usually it's
something we can help the author fix
with a little bit of concurrency magic
but yeah it's it's improved over time it
does happen but much less okay how does
the performance of JRuby compare to MRI
or other Ruby implementations I know you
strive to be the best are you we
generally are now
in it are obviously it's gonna depend
benchmark to benchmark if you take a
pure Ruby implementation of some
algorithm one that I use fairly
frequently is a pure ruby red black tree
implementation that we have a nice
benchmark for if you run that on JRuby
compared to C Ruby it's gonna be
anywhere from two to ten times faster on
JRuby JRuby is generally going to be
fastest and if you find something that's
slower on JRuby we would usually
consider it a bug there's no reason we
shouldn't be faster than C Ruby there's
also work going on part of Oracle labs
they have three or four people now
working on an implementation of JRuby on
top of their truffle runtime which is a
much more aggressive optimizing platform
than just running on top of the JVM
normally and they're getting close to
C++ performance it's early days for that
work but we believe with the truffle
work with our new ir and our new
optimizations we're able to do we're
going to be able to get real close to
straight-up Java performance over the
next year Wow impressive
if if I wanted to write a web
application in JRuby would I go with the
Ruby framework like rails or Sinatra or
choose one of the many Java based
frameworks would it be kind of governed
by like we were saying earlier sort of
what background I'm coming from sure we
definitely look at the background of
folks that are coming in so if you are a
Java developer that's familiar with Java
web frameworks and not interested in
trying one of the the Ruby frameworks
that are out there most of them do have
some amount of support for JRuby spring
for example has has ways that you can
declare beans as being from Ruby and
then it will load the Ruby code up and
then install it where it's supposed to
be play framework has support for it
vertex has support for it so you can use
Java frameworks with Ruby buy it by
going through JRuby we generally
recommend that if you're going to be
using Ruby though that you look at some
of the Ruby libraries that are out there
obviously rails is still very hard to
beat for quickly getting an application
up and going being able to
all of it quickly Sinatra is a very nice
neat fast environment for small services
you will find that it fits a little bit
better to have your application be a
ruby based framework if you're going to
be using JRuby but it is possible to use
the Java frameworks - okay that makes
perfect sense in episode 240 of the
podcasts here we were we talked about
groovy and you know at least in theory
groovy is just a jar file which makes it
possible to kind of sneak it into a Java
shop in theory does JRuby fit that
deployment model or does it require a
little bit more and thus you would have
to get kind of support from management
to bring it in we've actually some of
our best applications are our best users
have done exactly this they've snuck it
into a previously just Java environment
we have utilities to take a rails
application or a Sinatra application
bundle it up as a Java war file and
deploy it on any server and you know
your DevOps team will probably never
know the difference because it just
looks like another java application Wow
that makes perfect sense yeah once it's
down to a war file then yes just another
war file well and along the same lines
of the the question about whether you
should use Ruby or Java frameworks we
also say if you're in a Java environment
then go for it deploy it as a war file
it'll work just fine if you're not in a
Java environment or you don't have a
requirement to run on a normal Java
application server one of the ruby web
server libraries is probably going to be
just as good for you okay yes so then
you're not you're not even bound to a
particular deployment model yeah exactly
we kind of want it to fit both worlds so
if you're a rubyist it feels right or
you're a Java developer it feels right
ok I'm going to take a brief sidetrack
if we have time here to talk about
another language on the JVM that you've
had involvement with which is Mira
briefly what is Mira I wanted to create
a language that
and felt very similar to Ruby but it
would be statically typed it would
compile directly to JVM bytecode so it
didn't have any other library
dependencies once you once you finish
compiling and the idea was that Mira
might be an easier language for rubyists
who want to contribute to JRuby than
having them come in and try to write
Java code now that goal never really
happened we've continued to use Java
code pretty much everybody in the world
can write Java and it's very very well
supported by tools but mirror the
language has continued to live on
basically a statically typed Ruby like
language for the JVM with has IDE
support there's a number of folks using
it for production applications it's a
fun little language was the
implementation of it significantly
simpler than JRuby because of the
differences I mean for example just the
string thing that we were talking about
you could just say the semantics are
Java strings right absolutely so Mira
itself probably the biggest difference
from JRuby or Scala or groovy or any of
the other non Java languages on the JVM
it's just a compiler there's no core
classes that we have implemented in Mira
there's no runtime library that's
required there's no jar file for Mira it
replayed essentially isn't intended to
replace Java C in your compiler chain in
your build chain but with this Ruby like
language instead of regular Java the
goal being we want to try and have a
language that that fits that that niche
of well not even that niche that's what
most people want is a language that just
compiles down to a binary and doesn't
drag along this ball and chain so places
that you could use Java but maybe not
groovy
because of the large runtime it brings
well Mira fits right in that spot so
yeah I kind of start with a syntax
that's Ruby inspired and then kind of
take out a lot of problems and then
produce something that basically as you
said compiles to Java directly there
without a runtime right when one
comparison that's been made is Mira's
kind of the coffee
script of Java that fits even better
than that I was sort of thinking there's
a version of Python as it perhaps are
Python that has the Python syntax they
cleaned up they took out a fair amount
of the dynamic semantics so that they
could then compiled to native code right
exactly our Python it's probably a
pretty good analog our Python doesn't
have as much type declaration as Mira
does so Mira kind of follows the Scala
or c-sharp pattern where you need to
declare parameters two methods and
probably return values but that's that's
it whereas I think our Python you don't
have to clear to declare anything and
their magic compiler can figure it all
out
I never went that far because number one
doing full system type inferences was
beyond my abilities at the time I was
working on Mira and number two I don't
particularly mind the Scala and c-sharp
approach of local type inference just
requiring parameters to be declared I
thought that was a nice balance and it
certainly made the compiler easier to
write well that's great a great
explanation of sort of the trade-offs
there of kind of starting with that Ruby
syntax but then let's bring in some Java
things so it Maps much cleaner and
easier there so building on this
overview of JRuby I'd kind of like to
dive a little bit deeper into the JVM as
a platform for JRuby you've already
hinted at some of these things but is
JRuby or as you hinted at before JRuby
9000 is JRuby implemented with its own
intermediate representation or does it
compile to the byte Java source code I
guess not maybe java bytecodes
how does that work sure I can give a
basic overview of how it works
so JRuby has a an lalr parser for the
parser II geeks out there it's
essentially a port of mris bison grammar
so pretty much line for line port both
in the lexer and the parser part that's
all written in Java that takes Ruby code
in and gives us a tree an AST JRuby one
point seven then it would just interpret
that ast in 9000 we run an additional
compiler against that ast that gets
compiled into our own intermediate
representation basically our own
bytecode form then we can run our own
optimization passes on it we can
eliminate dead code we can propagate
values all the cool tricks that that
optimizing compilers can do we can do at
the Ruby level then eventually if a code
runs enough and it gets hot just like in
the JVM we will get it and in our case
that's cheating - JVM bytecode so we'll
do a little bit more analysis on the
code run a few more optimization passes
appropriate for byte code generation and
then spit out JVM bytecode and then the
JVM from there we'll we'll do a very
similar process that JVM bytecode goes
into the JVM intermediate representation
eventually it compiles down to native
code so really we've kind of built a
little VM on top of the JVM just because
we need to be able to have the the speed
and startup time of an interpreter but
eventually get up to full performance of
actual bytecode and then just in case
listeners didn't catch it when you say
jet it's just in time compilation or
transformation right right just-in-time
compilation which for us is simply a
counter if a method gets called 50 times
we figure it's hot enough to actually
compile into JVM bytecode okay what are
the advantages of that strategy it's it
sounds like there are several pieces to
it but ultimately I suppose what you're
aiming for his performance so the
advantages of having our own interpreter
are mostly startup time related if you
look at jvm languages that don't have an
interpreter like groovy like javascript
either in Rhino or in the nas horn I
think Rhino might have had an
interpreter mode as well but Nazz horn
the newer JavaScript Roman tation is all
compiled all bytecode those
implementations either have a big hit
compile-time and they have a
compile-time like in groovy you can just
run the groovy code but you typically
build it all if you don't build it ahead
of time they have to not only parse this
code in read it into memory they also
have to then generate byte code before
they can even execute well after we
parse we've got our own compiler pass
but we can get going much more quickly
by not having to generate the byte code
right away and then only generate the
byte code for the things that really
need it right the things that are
getting called frequently we read
exactly when you do generate byte code
is it difficult to produce byte codes
that the hotspot VM will recognize as
something that it knows how to optimize
is that something you're trying to
you're trying to fit its pattern
language so to speak yeah actually
there's a lot of work being done both in
JRuby and the on the JVM side by by
folks at Oracle to try and improve how
we can describe code in JVM bytecode
maybe that means better annotations are
better typing type systems and whatnot
we do spend a lot of time looking at the
JVM bytecode looking at what the JVM
actually does with it and trying to make
the to optimize the right way that was
part of the motivation of doing our own
intermediate representation in JRuby
9000 there's things that we know about
Ruby code that were too difficult to
convey in just straight-up JVM bytecode
the jaebeum just didn't see through it
and didn't optimize the way we wanted it
to
now with our own optimizing compiler on
top of the JVM we can do a little bit of
that work for the JVM and kind of just
use it as our native code back-end you
mentioned earlier about the
invokedynamic bytecode that was
introduced in Java 7 and that was
primarily to help languages other than
Java such as JRuby briefly what does
that do the bytecode so invokedynamic
was added in Java 7 after many years of
work and and discussion JRuby was was
right alongside that development so we
made sure it went well
invokedynamic is a bytecode that was
added to the JVM initially to provide a
way to do dynamic calls dynamic calls
that the JVM could still optimize and
see through just like other Java
indications most JVMs have the
capability of optimizing dynamic calls
because of the the nature of Java
sometimes it has to be able to die damn
dynamically figure out what the target
is for for example for an interface
invocation it doesn't know at compile
time what that actual type is going to
be so there's plumbing in there
essentially like a dynamic language it
actually has grown to do a lot more than
just dynamic calls in Java 8 the support
for lambdas Java's version of closures
from other languages lambdas are
bootstrapped using invoke dynamic
because you can run this code once you
can get it installed into the into the
call site into the bytecode of the
application and then optimize it just
like any other piece of java code
there's more features in Java 9 that are
going to be using invoke dynamic under
the covers just because it's it's
actually so flexible we can continue to
evolve the Java language without even
adding any more byte codes and in the
end for JRuby I would assume this
improves performance anything else does
it also kind of cut down on code size so
performance definitely is an improvement
it sometimes can take a little bit
longer to warm up if we use invoke
dynamic rather than just our own dynamic
dispatch mechanisms but the performance
is usually three to five times faster
than what we can do with our simulated
dynamic call sites so we get performance
out of it
most of my benchmarking is done with
invoke dynamic because it generally is
far and away better than not using it
code size also is reduced because we can
put more plumbing into the invoke
dynamic logic rather than having to use
our own dynamic call logic it shrinks
down the amount of byte code that we
generate but it may be more byte code or
may be more native code emitted once the
JVM actually can
Pyles it because it's doing a better job
of optimizing its inlining code where it
wouldn't before so that can kind of be a
trade off there'll be more code
executing at runtime but but less code
loaded into the JVM okay yeah I hadn't
even thought of the difference between
the Java byte code size and then the
native size how significant is it that a
byte code was added to the job of a Java
VM to support non Java languages well
until then there was it was the most
significant change ever
and really there haven't been a whole
lot since it's the first time ever that
any any bytecode any instruction was
added to the JVM and that's one of the
reasons that when we worked on
invokedynamic trying to design design
this feature we really wanted to make
sure it was as flexible as possible
making changes to the java language
specification are hard making changes to
the JVM specification are 10 times
harder because you need all of the JVM
vendors to agree on this and they all
have to make an implementation of it and
there's a lot more work that goes into
it so it's actually worked out really
well to make this one instruction be
super-powerful we haven't had to add
anything new to support things like
lambdas okay yeah I was gonna ask you if
there were any other bytecode changes
over the years but I guess not
as a minor aside what's the minimum
version of the JVM that one needs to run
JRuby do you need Java 7 so we support
two versions of JRuby right now the 1.7
line which is a couple years old now
we're going to maintain that until the
end of this year most people though
we're trying to get in to migrate over
to JRuby 9000 jrb 1.7 works on Java 6
and higher but we removed the Java 6
support for JRuby 9000 because we really
wanted to use invokedynamic more so Java
7 and up if you're going to be using
JRuby 9x you already mentioned that Java
8 added lambdas and since Ruby and
therefore JRuby have always had lambdas
and closures do the job
eight lambdas affect JRuby we get this
question quite a bit the interesting
thing about lambdas in Java eight is
that because of invokedynamic there were
almost no JVM changes and no JDK change
is really required to support it a
lambda is mostly just an on-the-fly
interface implementation like anonymous
inner classes where before it just gets
its own little class in memory that
class implements some interface and gets
passed into whatever API you're calling
we've already done that as well if you
have a Java call that you want to make
from Ruby and it takes an interface we
will automatically make the Ruby code
implement that interface for you so
we're essentially doing most of what
Java eight lambdas already did at a
language level and noting that the
lambda add it actually was necessary to
support those same features you don't
use the Java eight lambdas because
you're emitting byte codes and the only
bytecode there is invoke dynamic right
exactly and so we have very similar to
lambda when you have a closure in Ruby
we bootstrap that with invokedynamic
just like the Java 8 compiler does so
it's very similar techniques we've just
been doing them since before Java 8 even
started adding lambdas since one value
of using Ruby on the JVM via JRuby is
that you can use existing Java libraries
like you mentioned what are some of the
issues involved with interoperating with
Java and Java libraries you just
mentioned the the whole concept of
dynamically generating an interface and
whatnot so there's a few things
obviously the the dynamic nature of Ruby
at times you may have to give some more
hints calling Java code to know which
types are actually getting passed in say
that I need to call the string version
of this method rather than the numeric
version no we try to guess as much as
possible based on the actual types that
are coming in you probably meant to call
the in version versus the long version
or whatever but sometimes you'll need to
be more explicit about that let's see
what else is is challenging for Java
libraries so a lot of Java libraries
assume that you're going to have a
normal Java class somewhere in memory
that you can instantiate and call
methods on statically well obviously
Ruby classes are built dynamically as
your application loads so normally there
is no class no Java class that goes
along with a particular Ruby class so
that causes some problems integrating
with libraries we also have our own
object hierarchy which means if you want
a Ruby class to extend a Java class well
we don't have multiple inheritance on
the JVM so we have to do some some
clever indirection essentially make a
little proxy object that actually
extends the Java side and figure out how
to route calls around so mostly it ends
up being around the type system I guess
just the way that classes are structured
and the assumptions that the rest of the
JVM makes about what a class or what an
object looks like does the
interoperability work better in one
direction than the other I would think
JRuby calling into Java would be a
little easier than Java calling back
into JRuby for some of the reasons you
just mentioned right exactly it is much
easier to do the Ruby calling Java side
of that it's possible to do the Java
Java side calling Ruby we usually
recommend that if you want to do that
you have your Ruby code implement some
interface will generate a nice class for
it that fits into our object hierarchy
and it will look like a normal interface
implementation to Java code if you do
actually have to just do a straight-up
dynamic call into a ruby object we've
got some utility api's that you can call
through that make that a little bit
easier but the interface implementation
way is smooths most of the problems of
calling from Java into Ruby is it at all
practical to interoperate between two
non Java languages so suppose I've got
JRuby and Scala or JRuby and JSON yeah
we've talked about this at the JVM
language summits Java
those of us that work on jvm languages
and and the folks that work on the JVM
itself we've tried to come up with
clever ways that we can make language
Interop better it always seems to boil
back down to Java is just kind of the
lingua franca that we all end up
supporting so if you're calling from
JRuby into Scala with our array type
that array type is probably going to be
converted into a simple java array and
then turned into whatever Scala uses as
an array type we always go through Java
as our standard set of Interop types and
that works pretty well most of the time
most of the languages that are on the
JVM have very good integration with Java
itself so as long as we're going through
Java the languages can kind of talk to
each other right that makes perfect
sense I mean after all the the JVM is
there for Java and like you said it's
the lingua franca so kind of pulling out
a now into kind of bigger picture stuff
when we were talking about various
different languages on the JVM I tend to
think of one group of them as you know
professional languages or successors to
the two Java would be successors so
we've talked about Scala groovy
there's also Kotlin and Ceylon do you
think the existence of these other
languages helps or hinders traditional
Java well I'm coming from kind of a
biased share point being one of the you
know professional language developers on
the JVM I think it absolutely helps Java
it helps in that we get JVM improvements
for different language patterns that may
never have been considered and until
they were available for example
invokedynamic there was very little
interest in working on invoke dynamic
until there was a breakout hit dynamic
language on the JVM JRuby suddenly it
made sense to actually start pushing on
dynamic dispatch which ended up helping
Java in Java eight lambdas and other
Java 9 features I think it's also helped
encourage or
to get the Java train rolling again
lambdas had been wanted in Java for a
long time but until we saw people going
to closure and Scala and Ruby to get
them there wasn't a lot of energy put
into it once those languages became
well-established everybody saw how
powerful closures were Oracle had to put
the resources and time into actually
getting closures on on the Java language
as well so I I think it brings more
people to the platform and it just makes
the platform better it drives the
platform to improve that makes perfect
sense yeah I was I was thinking that the
at some point in time people picking up
these third-party languages and whatnot
for whatever their features are like
being able to do closures that would
then be kind of a driving force speech
behind adding those things to Java
certainly in my own personal experience
what you were talking about makes
perfect sense because I when I first
looked at closures I was like me but
then when I started working full-time or
nearly full-time with a language it
supported gnome I said wow this is
pretty cool yeah absolutely
well one pattern that I've seen over the
years now that we have these other
alternative jvm languages there's
hundreds thousands I don't know tens or
hundreds of thousands maybe of people
out there who never would have touched
the JVM if it was only Java but they
will use the JVM with closure they will
use the JVM with JRuby it's brought
people in that never would have even
been here so it can only be good for the
platform as far as I'm concerned
right yeah it's expanding the tent so to
speak in the recent few years there have
been a few new native languages like go
and rust do you think these pose a
challenge to jvm languages or are they
because they're native more targeting
domains like databases or operating
systems is it just really an apples and
oranges sort of thing well they bring a
lot of interesting new features the two
that you you mentioned specifically go
with its sort of event reactor
as part of the core language it's able
to crank up all these co-routines
run many different essentially vertical
threads of execution on much fewer
native threads that's definitely a
challenge for the JVM I've read through
the go run times code and you
essentially need to design that sort of
pattern that sort of micro threading
pattern into the run time from the
beginning there are some micro threading
libraries for the JVM but they're all
sort of hacky they use bytecode tricks
and you know they're not really doing
native VM level thread tricks like like
go does but the platform could do that
the platform could get support for true
native co-routines just like go has and
hopefully the interest in go and the
demand for that sort of feature will
drive the JVM to do it too on the rest
side if you're doing rust that's mostly
unmanaged code I think that would
probably be kind of difficult to bring
over to the JVM we want things to offer
everything's always gonna be garbage
collected so any managed memory or
unmanaged ap is for memory stuff would
have to be emulated in some way you know
pointer pointer tricks and allocate and
deallocate that kind of stuff don't fit
into the JVM pattern well but the other
language features that are in rust could
certainly be done on the JVM I have done
little prototypes of cocoa routines I've
wanted to try and do a rust on the JVM
maybe with reduced features but but the
interesting thing about all of these off
platform languages is that they're
showing us new ways of looking at
problems JRuby is the most successful
off platform language to come to the JVM
if you look at Scala enclosure and
groovy and Kotlin and all the other
professional languages on the JVM they
were written for the JVM to begin with
JRuby by virtue of needing more out of
the JVM has helped drive the platform
probably more than those languages with
native support and with dynamic
invocation so I think as those other
languages get popular and show us cool
features the JVM communities
want those features and we'll probably
see something come around and so I think
you've already answered this question
but what do you think about the future
or the outlook for Java the non Java
languages and the JVM itself so ignoring
politics around Java in the JVM since
that's that be worthy of an entire other
podcast technology-wise tech wise I
think the JVM in Java the Java platform
are incredibly healthy and continuing to
grow they are bringing in language
developers doing all sorts of new cool
stuff with some unusual languages in
some cases I the jaebeum's
I don't know if it'll probably abel
outlive java job is kind of the see of
the JVM pretty much everything is Java
at some level even if it's just going to
bytecode but I think the JVM is going to
survive a long time we have a real open
source implementation that anybody can
use and build and modify and distribute
we have lots of different languages that
are available and more being created
every day this is the best platform
available for for new language work and
I think it's going to continue to be
successful for a long time oh great
platform for new language development
that's exactly of the theme of the show
so in closing is there anything else
that you'd care to mention about the JVM
is a language platform let's see well I
I think folks that are interested in
building a new language if you want a
managed runtime you don't want to have
all the objects management yourself you
don't want have to write a JIT and a GC
it's it's definitely the best platform
to look at it's certainly the best
managed runtime that's out there and and
by far the best open source managed
runtime that's available and I you know
I would encourage folks that our JVM
Java developers to have a look at JRuby
take a look at what people are doing if
Ruby try it out and know that you can
still call all the same libraries and
deploy to the same servers if you need
to but you can get the benefits of
frameworks like Ruby and rails and
probably become a
a better developer by by trying out some
new patterns in your own apps so where
can people get a hold of you or follow
your work I'll include links to anything
so don't feel obligated to spell any
URLs out of something sure I I welcome
anybody to tweet questions at me if you
want have a private conversation you can
find me at heady at heaviest calm on
pretty much any of the chat services the
JRuby project itself is home dat JRuby
org which has links to download links to
our github project site and the wiki all
of our issues trackers and whatnot so
JRuby org will get you there if you are
already a ruby user and you're using one
of the Ruby switchers like our VM or
Ruby build Ruby install those all
support JRuby too so it should just be a
matter of our VM install JRuby and
you've got JRuby locally to play with
and the JRuby project open-source
I assume it's an open community
welcoming yeah absolutely it's all open
source it's all on github under the
JRuby organization we've got JRuby
itself and a bunch of other supporting
projects and we are always looking for
folks to help out there's a several
hundred open items in the bug tracker
that can be worked on and we even marked
a few for for new contributors so try
out JRuby and and maybe you can help us
make it better great well thanks for
your time Charlie I've really enjoyed
our discussion and I hope our listeners
will too this is Charles Anderson for
software engineering radio thanks for
listening to se radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SD -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on iTunes
mention a message us on twit
at SC radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at SC - radio net this and
all other episodes of SU radio is
licensed under the creative commons 2.5
license thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]